So in this video we're going to start revisiting variables again, right? We have some business
left with variables. So let's just go in and dive into what remains or variables to be seen.
Obviously we keep on using variables different way right across the scores and in your program
in your development or your developer journeys. But this is very important for you to understand
how variables behave depending on where you declare and use them. So by now we know that
we have two types of variables in Java that is primitive variables at reference variables
or you can just call them primitive type variables at reference type variables. But we have then
three levels of variables as well that is two types and three levels. What are levels now?
Levels are where exactly at what places can you declare variables in Java? And there are
three places to be exact. There are three places to be appropriate. And depending on where you
declare them, they would have their repercussions, right? So let's just have a look at them.
There are three levels as I said where you can declare variables. Both these types of variables
mind, mind you that is reference as well as primitives. We can declare these two types of variables
at three levels in Java. The first level is called instance level variables. And once you
declare these variables at the instance level, then then appropriately called instance variables
in Java, and which is the instance level. Let me just go on and show you that. I'll just quickly
go on and create a new class for that. I'll just call it variable level work. Again, I appropriately
calling them as I've been telling you across the course, we should always pay attention to what
we name our identifier. They go a long way in your code being better readable. So again, we'll just
maximize this window for you. So this is variable level of work. I'll just have this as the main
method. Now let's say I have another function or method here and move on methods that's coming
on for you in the next video where we are going to look at methods or functions from absolute
scratch again. And that would just give you an understanding of why do we use methods? How do we
use them in the Java programming language? But for now, just understand that like main, we have
our own under the method. I'll just call it white funk, for example, and you do something here,
and you have, let's say, white MIT short for method. And you do something here, right? Now,
which is the instance level, right? But to get started with first things first, there is no such
concept as a global variable in Java that practice was stopped with C++. We cannot do that.
There's no such concept in reality in Java. There's no such concept as a global variable.
That means you cannot define a variable outside of a class that's not permissible, right?
What is permissible is what I told you within the class at the instance level and that instance
level is this. I'll just put that as dashes for you. And obviously, comment that.
So, just have a look at where exactly can we declare these variables that means either here,
or here, or here, or at the bottom, but still within the class. And that is
instance variables that instance level is when you declare variables of a class,
either of those two, by the way, primitive and reference variables at within the class,
but outside every method C within the class, but outside mean within the class still, but outside
funk within the class, but outside funk and MIT and main and within the class outside all methods.
So, within the class, but outside every method, we call them as instance variables, right?
So, technically, we can declare them at the top or in between the methods or at the bottom,
right? But why would we define variables in between the methods that would just make it look ugly,
right? And I'm all of for writing better readable as you know me now, and code quality should be
of the of the priority here, right? So, why would we declare them? Although we can, but we should
not declare them or we would not declare them within methods. So, either you can stick them to be
declared at the top or at the bottom in your projects, you might see one of these approaches,
but right across the scores will stick to declaring them at the top.
That's how I find them better readable, but as I told you in your projects, don't be surprised
if you see them being declared at the bottom, but still within the class, right? And for now,
I'll just go ahead and declare a variable right here. And again, it can be any variable either
permit your reference. Let me just go ahead and I'll say int value, right? Okay. And then I'll say,
for example, let me just declare it up type Boolean, I'll just call it is acting, right?
Now, these are instance level variables. These are instance variables of the class variable level
or right. But as I said, you could have declared them between methods at the bottom would make no
difference, right? To how they behave, because these are all instance variables. And in this class,
I have two variables of type primitive level instance for it, re emphasis type primitive,
because both are int and Boolean, right? And level is instance. So, now, the next thing is
to know, what does it mean for you to declare a variable at level instance? So again, first things first,
instance variables, you should note it down, right? If you are taking notes, or just remember it,
and obviously when you do a handsome, get your hands dirty. So, right, a lot of code tinker with
them and you would know, what do I mean by saying instance level variables in Java are created,
they are given memory, right? They're allocated memory at the time. And whenever we create an
object of the class, again, I'll just put it for reiteration instance level variables of a class
are allocated memory, they exist at the time. And whenever we create an object of the class,
so that is before you create an object of a class, this is just pure English, nothing else,
right? Okay. So, and no matter how many objects you create in the class, those many times,
the instance variables would be created, right? So, more than that in some time,
but for now, do you know the first property again, instance variables, they exist after you create
an object of the class, and whenever you create an object of class, right? So, that means,
in this class, if you have a look at it, I am not created an object of this class,
variable level of work, that means value and is active do not exist, they just do not exist,
right? And that is why they cannot be called, if you do something like this,
it should be an error. I'll say doesn't exist yet, right? That's why an error,
I'll just comment the entire line would not work, all right? And that brings me to the second
property of instance variables, they can then be accessed with the dot operator using that instance,
right? Because every instance, that is instance variables or let me just rephrase it for you to
understand it clearly and simply, and that is instance variables or every object of the class
has its own copy of the instance variables. Remember what I told you, right? Whenever we create an
object of the class, that means every object of the class has its own copy of the instance
variables, that is the second property, I'm telling you, the third property rather, the second one
being that they're then accessible by that dot operator to use that instance. So, that means,
if I say variable level work, and I'll just call it rep to new variable level work,
I've created an instance of this class as I told you the syntax to do so in Java, and then you say
ref dot the scroll is active, and I'll say also, see, no error this time. Why? Because
exist now, and accessible by its object, because it belongs to an object, which is referred to by
the reference variable that is REF, right? That's how we have called it ref dot instance variable,
that is reference variable dot, and then the property name this time it's active, and similarly,
you could have called ref dot value, and put in the value that you want it to be hold,
and that just works, right? So, that is, when I say they can be called with their own instances
using the dot operator, and similarly, let's say I create another object of this class, I'll just
call other ref to new variable level work, that's the object, and I say other ref dot value is
equal to its 70, and guess what? This object, which is referred to by other ref, would have its
value inside this value variable, its 70, but ref dot value would still be 900, why? Because every
object of the class has its own copy of the instance variables, right? That means, if you change
the value once, it would not reflect those updates anywhere else, because everyone has its own
copy, right? And a great analogy that comes to my mind right here is, let's say, in a game of
football or cricket, let's say in football, who's your favorite player? I know it should be
Lionel Messi or Cristiano Ronaldo, or in the cricket, who's your favorite player? Maybe
Verat Coley or Stephen Smith, or for example Mitchell's stock, or even just played Bumura,
right? Now, let's say God forbid, Messi is injured, does it mean that, or Messi's arm is injured,
or Messi's leg is injured to be appropriate, right? Because we play football with the legs,
so Messi's leg is injured, all footballers have the property legs, right? So, but Messi's
leg is injured, does it mean all other 10 players are injured as well? They've injured the legs,
absolutely not, right? Because every object, Messi, like all those 10 other players in that
football team, have their own copy of the legs, right? So, Messi's legs were injured,
does not mean everyone else was injured. Similarly, with, let's say, just be Bumura got forward,
he injured his back, does it mean every other player in the team would injure their back? No,
not necessarily, right? And it's the rarest of rarest scenarios, right? Why? Because just
because Bumura has access to his own back while others have the same back, but their own copy,
right? That's a great analogy. Just think about it, ponder about it, and you will know what I mean.
So, coming back, so this is why Rev.valu would have its own value, other Rev.valu would have its own
value, right? And, and that is how instance variables work. And the fourth property I'm going to
tell you about is instance variables in Java have default values, right? I told you there's no
such concept as a garbage value, like there was in C and C++, it doesn't exist in Java,
but they have instance variables. If you declare variables at the instance level,
they have default values depending on what type of variable you declare.
If you declare the variable as Boolean at the instance level, it has the default value of false.
If you declare it of type byte or short or in or long, they have the default value that is zero.
If you declare a variable of type care, they have the default value that is slash u 000,
which is pronounced as the null character. If you declare a variable at the instance
level of type float or double, they have the default value of 0.0. And, if you declare a variable of
type reference, right, reference variables, right, what would they have? They would have the default
value of null, right? The any kind of a variable sort of depending on the type that you declare,
these would have default values. That means when I declare value at the instance level,
because see it is at the instance level within the class, but outside every method,
it would have the default value of zero, right, even if you do not initialize it,
is active, would have the default value of, you get to write the response. And, if I declare
a variable of type reference, that is, let's say variable level work, let's call it work,
what would it have, default value of null. I'll say, null. This is false. This is zero.
Depending on what I told you, what is the type of variable that you would declare, right?
So, these are instance level variables. And, they live the last property, what instance variables
are going to tell you about is, they live as long as the object is aligned, right? As long as
the object is alive, you can just call them with the dot operator, right? But, once the object is
no longer there, instance variables are also said to be lost or dead depending on the context,
but they cannot be exist, right? So, in the next video, we're going to talk about the second
and the third level of variables. Again, where you, if you declare them at those levels,
they would have their own properties and the behavior would change significantly.